<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Propositions from the Kings Majesty to His Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax: in two messages from the Isle of Wyght, dated Novem. 26. and Novem. 27. 1647. For the composing of all differences, and fulfilling the desires of all interests in the Kingdome. Also his Excellencies answer, in presence of His Officers. And Sir John Barckleys declaration concerning the extent of the message sent by him from his Majesty.  Novemb: 30: 1647: These propositions from His Majesty in two messages to His Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax, were written with His Majesties own hand, subscribed Charles Rex</title>
            <author>Charles I, King of England, 1600-1649.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79046</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C2726</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E418_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204602</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864069</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864069</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161333</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79046)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161333)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 66:E418[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Propositions from the Kings Majesty to His Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax: in two messages from the Isle of Wyght, dated Novem. 26. and Novem. 27. 1647. For the composing of all differences, and fulfilling the desires of all interests in the Kingdome. Also his Excellencies answer, in presence of His Officers. And Sir John Barckleys declaration concerning the extent of the message sent by him from his Majesty.  Novemb: 30: 1647: These propositions from His Majesty in two messages to His Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax, were written with His Majesties own hand, subscribed Charles Rex</title>
                  <author>Charles I, King of England, 1600-1649.</author>
                  <author>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, Baron, 1612-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Ibbitson in Smithfield,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In fact consisting only of the two messages from Charles I.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: staining.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Dec: 1st".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Captivity, 1647-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Treaties --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161333:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PROPOSITIONS FROM THE KINGS MAJESTY To His Excellency Sir THOMAS FAIRFAX: In Two Meſſages from the Iſle of WYGHT, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Novem.</hi> 26. <hi>and Novem.</hi> 27. 1647.</p>
            <p>For the compoſing of all differences, and fulfilling the <hi>Deſires of all Intereſts in the Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo His Excellencies Anſwer, in preſence of His Officers. And Sir <hi>John Berckleys</hi> Declaration con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the extent of the Meſſage ſent by him from His Majeſty.</p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Novemb: 30: 1647:</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THeſe Propoſitions from His Majeſty in Two Meſſages to His Excellency Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> were written with His Majeſties own hand, Subſcribed</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>CHARLES REX:</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>Charles I's royal blazon</figDesc>
               <p>C R</p>
               <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENS</q>
               <q>DIEV ET MONDROIT</q>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Robert Ibbitſon</hi> in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:161333:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:161333:2"/>
            <head>PROPOSITIONS From the KINGS MAIESTIE To His Excellency SIR <hi>THOMAS FAIRFAX:</hi> In two Meſſages from the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> dated <hi>Novem.</hi> 26. and <hi>No.</hi> 27. 1647. for the compoſing of all differences, and fulfilling the deſires of all Intereſts in the Kingdome. <hi>The firſt Meſſage.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <signed>CHARLES REX.</signed>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving left order at our remove from <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> that a copy ſhould be given you, of what we had then written to both Houſes of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:161333:3"/> Parliament touching the cauſes of our withdrawing, and the continuance of our Reſolutions to improve every oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of the ſatisfaction of all chief in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, that ſo a happy peace may bee ſetled in our Dominions: In purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance whereof, we have lately ſent a Meſſage to both Houſes from this place, and a copy of it to you: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſirous in order to that bleſſed worke, to give you our preſent ſenſe upon the condition of affaires as they now ſtand: VVee have thought fit to appoint Sir <hi>John Barckley</hi> to repair unto you, and to communicate the ſame to you: And we ſhall be glad by him to receive a mutual communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your ſenſe alſo, upon this ſubject; not doubting, but you eaſily perceive by the late diſorders, into what a depth of confuſion the Army and the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:161333:3"/> will fall, if timely and effectuall preventions be not uſed, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee have now againe propoſed (as the only expedient) a perſonall Treaty, for the compoſing of all diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, and fulfilling the deſires of all intereſts, to which if you will imploy your credit, as you cannot but expect the Bleſsings of God upon your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours therein; ſo may you juſtly look for the beſt returne that ever our condition ſhall be able to make you.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at <hi>Carisbrooke</hi> Caſtle,
<date>the 26. day of <hi>Novem.</hi> 1647.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>For Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> Generall.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:161333:4"/>
            <head>The Second Meſſage.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>Charles Rex,</signed>
            </opener>
            <p>THe free liberty which you willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly afforded <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s to have of the uſe of Our Chaplains, makes <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s at this time not onely to acknowledge your former ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilities, but likewiſe now to acquaint you that three of Our Chaplains, to wit, Dr. <hi>Sheldon,</hi> Dr. <hi>Holdſworth,</hi> and Dr <hi>Haywood,</hi> are newly landed in this Iſle, not doubting but they ſhall have the ſame protection that formerly they had, which ſtill will ſhew the continuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Your good reſpect unto <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, which we upon all fitting occaſions ſhall not bee backward to acknowledge, So Wee bid You heartily farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Given at</hi> Carisbrooke <hi>Caſtle</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>the 27 of Nov. 1647.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>For Sir Thomas Fairefax General.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:161333:4"/>
            <head>His Excellencies Anſwer to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Meſſage in preſence of His Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, And Sir <hi>John Barckleys</hi> Declaration concerning the Extent of the Meſſage ſent by Him to His Majeſty.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have ſent you incloſed brought yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day to the Generall from His Majeſty by Sir <hi>John Barckeley,</hi> Dated at <hi>Carisbrooke</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Novem.</hi> 26. and 27. The Generall being very tender of admitting any intercourſe with the <hi>King</hi> or any from him reſolved not to have any diſcourſe in private with Him, nor any thing in publique, but what might be for His better Accomodation, or the like, but for the matter of a Perſonall Treaty His Excellency could give no Anſwer to it the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:161333:5"/> Parliament having it under conſideration: The General having thus expreſſed His ſenſe to Sir <hi>John Barckeley</hi> in the preſence of His Officers, Sir <hi>John</hi> declared, He had nothing more in command, then to deſire his media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for a Perſonall Treaty, and ſo departed.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Novemb.</hi> 30. 1647.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Gilb. Mabbot.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
